To be a orders. I will
know many of you.
I'm the Director for
the Centre for Learning
Enhancement and
Educational Development
here at Manchester
Metropolitan University,
and we are hosting myself and
my colleagues hosting
this conference,
which is our third
summer learning and
teaching conference on the
theme of relational education,
and I'm really looking forward
to unpacking that with you.
Over the next two days.
As I said, the conference
this year bigger and
better than ever before.
We've got two days.
Today is online.
Tomorrow is on campus
in the business school.
We've got two fantastic
keynotes to bring you
and more space to really
celebrate our educators here,
our amazing educators
here at Manchester Met.
So it's lovely to see
you all this morning.
I'm going to hand over to
our P Vice Chancellor for
Education and Deputy Provost,
Professor Andy Dainty,
who's going to
add a few words of
welcome. Thank you.
Thanks, C morning, everyone.
Great to see you all.
Theo has told me to
be extremely brief.
That's exactly what
I'm going to be.
I think since lead
resurrected this conference,
it's just gone from
strength to strength.
It's always a joy and
pleasure and that
we've had to extend it
over two days this year
is absolutely fantastic.
I think it shows the level of
enthusiasm and engagement
with all things,
teaching, learning,
innovation in the university.
I just wanted to say a
couple of words about that.
If I look at the journey that
the university has been on,
over the last four
years and the kind
of changes that I've observed.
I don't just mean in terms of
league tables and metrics and
TEF God and all that kind of
stuff, which is
really important.
I mean in terms of the
way that colleagues have
engaged with
pedagogical innovation,
the number of promotions that
we've seen under
the EPPC pathway,
which now outstrips the re
pathway, I'm delighted to say.
The engagement not just
from academic staff,
but from our technical staff,
from our professional services
staff many of whom are now
senior fellows of HTA and going
for principal fellowship of HTA,
it's been quite
significant change,
and I think we should be really
pleased about that and we should
perhaps reflect on
the importance of
these kind of events in
enabling us to share
that practise,
to have those conversations,
perhaps challenge
each other's practise
as well in the
interests of supporting
our students an enormous amount
of effort and energy
goes into organising
an event like this.
I just want to begin
by thanking all of
my colleagues in the lead for
putting together such
a fabulous event.
We've got two brilliant keynotes
about to hear from Wong.
I'm really looking
forward to those.
But these events are not
easy to put together
and Fn and colleagues
a huge debt of gratitude for
all the work they've done.
Make sure if you do one thing
over the next two days,
make sure that you engage with
people that you don't normally
engage with You know,
speak to people from
different departments,
different academic disciplines,
different job families,
share some ideas,
bounce ideas off people.
But most importantly of all,
make sure you have some fun.
It's been a busy academic year.
It's been a great,
fantastic academic year.
We achieved an awful lot.
Everybody in the university
has been working really hard
on curriculum transformation
over the last two years.
We're coming to the end
of that process now,
and the university is
in a fantastic place.
I know that because if I look
out of my window to my left,
I can see thousands of
people across our campus
for our open day
today and we're still
the second most
popular university in
the UK and we should and
should continue to
celebrate that.
We hold that status for
a very good reason.
Have a fantastic conference,
really looking forward to today,
but hopefully I'll see some
of you in person tomorrow.
I look forward to
coming along to
the parallel
sessions. Thanks, E.
Thank you very much, Andy.
So now I am super
excited now to be able
to welcome and introduce
Professor Jason Ara,
who is Professor of
Sociology and Education at
the University of Cambridge and
professorial Fellow
of Jesus College.
Now, the title of
Jason's talk is We built
this City Belonging and
authenticity in Pedagogy.
But we're going to do things
a little bit differently.
This isn't going to be a
traditional keynote where
Jason's going to stand
up and speak to us.
We're actually going to do it in
the style of a fireside chat.
So imagine me and Jason
sitting in our armchairs.
The fire is blazing,
I mean, it's warm outside.
Wrong time of year,
perhaps, for that analogy.
But, um, We're going to give it
our best shot
completely unrehearsed.
So we'll and I've never
met Jason before,
so that it's either going
to work, or it's not.
I hope it's going to work, and
I'm really looking
forward to it.
If you have questions for Jason,
I'm really going
to try and allow
a little bit of time
at the end for those,
but I think it's um because
it's an online talk.
If you could post them in
the chat and then we'll
try and kind of run
through those afterwards.
I think that's probably the
easiest way to do that,
and we'll come back
to them at the end.
So I am going to
hand over to Jason,
and my first question
is really just one for
you to kind of just
introduce yourself a
little bit more and what
inspired you to pursue
a career in sociology.
That's great. Firstly, it's
such a privilege and a blessing
to be here with all
of you this morning.
Most important thing I'll ask
you is how you're keeping.
I really hope you're well,
really, really hope you're well.
I just want to say,
as well, and this is
really important.
I'll say it a couple of times,
but Valeria and Stuart
have been unbelievable.
They've been incredible.
And I cannot thank them both
enough for all their endeavour
and all their hard work.
I'm immensely grateful
to them both.
And yeah, this one is
definitely 72 today.
So thank you so much.
And I I guess what
inspired me into an academic
career or doing sociology.
Well, in a previous life,
I was a PE teacher,
so I always had
some sensibility around kind
of wanting to think
about how things were
done differently,
and it was actually
to do with a lot of
the experience I had
before university.
So my mom was an activist
and someone that taught me a lot
about I was very fortunate
to have the mother I did,
who taught me a lot
about social causes,
and I guess it's
kind of ingrained into you
from a very young age.
And I was very
fortunate I had that
because I'm not sure
I don't think I don't think
this is common knowledge.
I think it is, but I don't
have a sociology degree.
So I taught myself in
the middle of the night
doing shift work at
Sainsbury's less
than ten years ago,
which is the truth.
I So I taught myself how
to be a sociologist,
but in some respects,
I guess everybody has
some understanding of how the
world revolves around them.
And as my mom kind of
always said to me,
everybody's life has purpose and
everybody's life has meaning,
and we all have
something to say.
And if that purpose is
greater than your own need,
then you'd be amazed where
where Fortuna could smile
on you in terms of life.
And I've been very,
very fortunate that I'm
not good at many things,
but in fact, I was
literally saying
to a group of people
yesterday for Keno, I did.
You know, there's a concept
of business acumen.
I do not have any academic
acumen whatsoever,
but I always refer
to the Muhammad Ali quote
about will versus skill.
I never had the skill,
but I did have an
immeasurable will,
and I think skill can be
measured, but will can't.
And I guess in terms
of holding being
fortunate to hold any kind of
space in academia, hopefully,
maybe I'm some sort
of case study or
advertisement that
if the purpose
is greater than your own need,
you know, you'd be surprised and
kindness is at the base of
everything that you do.
You'd be surprised how
far that can take you.
Thank you, Jason. That's really
interesting reflections,
and I love that quote, actually.
And I'm sure that
will resonate with
a few colleagues in the room.
So, can we sort of
turn our attention to the
theme of the conference,
which is relational education?
And I'd really like
to hear from you
how you understand
the concept of
relational education and why you
think it's important to building
an excellent student experience,
particularly for marginalised
groups in higher education?
Sorry, if that's
a long question.
I can break it down if you.
No, no, not at all. So I
guess in terms of thank
you so much Sina,
I guess why do I think relational
education is important?
I mean, I think there's
several tenets and components to
a lot of these kind of
conceptual concepts.
But for me, it's always been
about simplifying things.
So, in essence, when I think
about education, what
do I think about?
I fundamentally think we're
dealing with human beings.
And the greatest admiration
I've always had for educators
are people who take
very difficult concepts
and make them very
simple to understand.
Now, the great thing with being
a school teacher
is that it's kind
of within the wheelhouse of
what school teachers do.
They take difficult concepts
and make them easy
to understand.
And when I came into
higher education in 2012,
the one thing that I learned
very quickly is that people
take very easy concepts
and make them more
difficult to understand.
So, you know, you
become really aware
Of the kind of
mechanisms that exist,
for example, you know,
postgraduate higher
education certificates
in terms of how you develop
that teaching, you know,
fellowship to the HEA HA.
In terms of that
type of fellowship,
you look at these kind
of different mechanisms
to improve your artistry,
to improve your armoury,
in terms of what you
can do pedagogically.
But if I kind of stripped it
all back and made it simple,
and I guess maybe one
thing that I am good at
pedagogically speaking
is making things
simple to understand,
but that's because
my own level is,
you know, it's modest.
So So I always thought, Okay,
what how can I make things
if I can understand it,
you know, and I surmount
my understanding
to a 7-year-old.
And there's no shame
in that, by the way,
because if I can take a concept
and a 7-year-old can
understand it, that's
a very good thing.
So I kind of always
relate myself to,
I have the understanding
of a 7-year-old.
If I can understand it and I can
make others understand
it, then that's great.
And then it's when
you kind of go
through the pedagogical
gears of turning up
the volume or going through
the gears in terms of
the difficulty of complexity
of what you're trying to say.
But if I was to
strip it all down,
it comes down to,
for me, humanity.
It comes down to seeing
individuals and
valuing human beings.
And in that space, you kind of
have to have this
really powerful elixa
of humility and vulnerability
in that pedagogical space,
and that relational bit comes
from in my experience and in
my belief that an
individual can look at
you and you become
either you know,
you become relatable to them.
You are relatable by
proxy of you existing.
They can see themselves and
they can see themselves in you
and you can see
yourself in them.
And I think that's
hugely, hugely important.
And that relational bit,
for me, is the hidden
curriculum bit.
You know, it's the
hidden crulum.
It's the bit where
the magic happens
where it's enough for
a learner to just give it
five more percent just
because maybe they
like that person.
And by the way, that 5% could
be a difference between
getting a 22 or
21 or getting a 21 and a
first or failing in passing.
But that relational
bit becomes so,
so important, and
it's in the kind
of minutiae of the detail.
The things that we don't
see in terms of what we do.
That relational bit is,
for example, remembering
someone's name, you know,
asking them how
their day has been,
you know, more than what
they had for breakfast.
It moves beyond relation
moves beyond transactional.
And because of the pressures
of kind of engaging
pedagogically,
we can often find ourselves in
this kind of
transactional transit,
whether that's working
with professional staff,
other academics or students.
But I think the most
important thing is to kind of
keep that relational aspect
by treating people
as human beings.
And because unfortunately,
university of
businesses We're not always
in situations where we do that.
And I think that relational
pedagogical bit,
that's where the
magic happens because
the knowledge in some
ways is disposable.
It's disposable, but
it's not the knowledge
that necessarily people
remember, it's the experience.
And if they've had a
very good experience,
more often than not,
they will be able to
remember the knowledge that
they've encountered
or experienced.
Mm. I love that notion
of of having humility
and vulnerability,
and essentially, you know,
they sit at the heart of
what it is to be human.
And that's what
education is about,
isn't it? It's about people.
It's about being it's
about being there for
our students and recognising
them as individuals.
And, yeah, that's fantastic.
Thank you for that.
Can I ask you a question?
How do you see it?
Yeah. Oh, gosh, I
wasn't prepared for me to
answer questions here.
I took a swivel.
I totally agree with you.
I mean, I think that
the idea of being,
I mean, another
word that stirred
about is authentic, isn't it?
Just being your real self.
And I think what you say
that speaks you know,
I've been around in
education long enough to
remember when it
was very much you
were kind of the
sage on the stage.
You know, I know
everything. My jobs to
impart what I know
into your head.
You'll write it
down and hopefully
you'll learn it
and pass the exam.
And we just live in such
a different world now,
I certainly certainly in my
lecture theatres, we do,
and I hope a majority of
colleagues here today think that
that it's about being there for
our students learning
with our students,
learning from our students,
our students learning
from each other,
and those relationships
and You know,
I just I sit at the heart of it.
They really do. So I'm
absolutely with you on it.
And I don't want
to talk too much
because people hear
from me every day.
They don't hear from you, so
I'm going right back at you, Ja.
Well, I don't. So this is
for my own selfishness.
Anyway, no, okay,
that's brilliant.
So let's build on that and
just think about how you
touched a little bit of
what academics can do
to implement relational
education around sort of,
you know, just acknowledging
people's names and the
sort of day they've had,
but are there any other
kind of tips that we
can take in terms of how we
prioritise that
relational education
in often challenging
circumstances.
We don't have endless time.
We don't have small
groups of students.
So how do we prioritise that?
Particularly looking at kind
of marginalised
minoritized groups?
Yeah, I think that's a
really great question.
Look, I first thing,
I always preface
everything I do by saying,
I do not have all the answers.
I can only go on what my um
wisdom tells me, really.
And I think a big part
of how we prioritise
those types of endeavours is
around it's around
the politics of care,
you know, all the
ethics of care.
I think it comes back to Again,
how we value people,
how we value people.
Can we work in models
of distributed leadership,
in terms of, you know,
eliminating hierarchy,
in terms of how we
work with learners,
in terms of, you know,
particularly minoritized learners?
I think the most important
thing is about being seen and
fostering cultures and fostering
environments that allow people,
and you mentioned
this word, Fiona.
It's my favourite word, apart
from humility on planet Earth,
to be their true
authentic selves.
You know, I think contrary
to popular belief,
not everybody has the privilege
of being able to be their
true authentic self.
A lot of people have to
adopt several different
guises just to survive,
you know, what can be
a pretty thorny intersectional
environment, you know,
whether that might be somebody
from a socially a difficult
socioeconomic background,
whether it may be on
the base of gender,
sexuality, you know,
race, religion.
So I think these things,
disability, I think it's really,
really important how we think
about seeing people,
you know, and again,
it comes back to this thing
that I talk about all the time,
treating people as
human beings and value,
seeing that everybody's
life has value.
And it is difficult because of
the increasing student numbers.
But, you know, this
isn't a life or death,
you know, literally speaking.
But I think those experiences
can make the difference in
someone's life in terms of
somebody who is
facing, you know,
mentally a life or
death situation,
just seeing that
individual, can make
all the difference in
that individual believing that
there might be a tomorrow.
And, you know, that's why
every interaction
has to have meaning.
That's my personal belief.
Like, and I understand
the numbers I've asked.
It's very difficult to do that,
but every interaction
has to have meaning.
I always work on the premise
that if this might be
the first or last time
I might see someone.
But I'm going to
give them my best.
I'm going to give them
my absolute best.
I'm going to give them because
I'm going to give them my time.
I'm going to give them my love,
I'm going to give
them everything I
can in that small interaction.
And is that a
difficult thing to do?
Yes, it is. Is it sustainable?
Maybe I'm a cautionary
tale that it might not be.
But I think your custodians
in this place and
your job to kind of
quote an all blacks
mantra is that your job
is to leave the jersey in
a better condition
than you found it.
And part of that, for me,
it's always been about giving
it everything you've got.
I never proclaimed to be
the best at anything,
but what I did always expect
or demand from myself
is that you give it
your absolute best
because if somebody
hadn't done that for me
before going to university,
I wouldn't even be sat
here in front of you now.
So it's that whole
thing of, you know,
I remember Sandro saying
to me when I left college,
he said, he's from Brazil,
and he's my best friend, but
also was my teacher, as well.
And he said, and I bought
in this Brazilian shirt,
and he said, Jason, I really
appreciate this gift.
But, you know, the one thing
I'm going to say to you is,
um, In the whole
time I've known you,
have I ever said no to you?
And I said, no, no,
no, you haven't.
And he said, Okay, you see
everything I've done for you,
the best gift you could give me
is if you do the same
for everyone else.
And I was like, Yeah,
yeah, that's easy.
I said, No, no, that
means you've always
got to give it everything
you've got with every student.
And it's easy to
say that at 20-years-old
that you'll do it.
So 20 years later.
Having spent the last
15 years doing it,
you realise how easy he
made it look and how
difficult it actually is.
But it always means everything
because the belief I always had,
which is a very personal one,
is that I would hope that
the love and compassion
and the ability to
make people feel seen,
particularly ethnic
minority, people from
ethnic minority
backgrounds, and feel seen
In spaces that have
historically excluded,
you know, ethnic
minorities in particular.
Everything that I have
done, I have children.
I have two children,
and I always hope
that the way I
always try to treat
other people's
children as though
they were my own.
And so I always hope that
when it's my children's turn,
my daughter's 18, so she's
going to university,
this year that, you know,
whatever good I've done for
other people, hopefully,
hopefully somebody
when my daughter
finds herself in a
bind all my youngest,
that people will do
the same for them.
So that was always a huge
extrinsic motivator.
But the intrinsic
motivator was that
I know how powerful education
and instrument can be,
and it sounds like a very
obvious thing to say,
but I know what it can
do in terms of changing
people's lives because
it did the same for me.
So I was always even
more driven and more
motivated to help as many
students as possible.
And, you know, Everyone
will have different
approaches on that
in terms of their
limits and stuff.
My attitude to life,
which is kind of a cautionary
tale of what not to do,
is to run it until
the wheels fall off,
and that's probably
not sustainable,
and it means that I
probably won't be doing
this her in five
or ten years time.
But if I look back at the body
of work and the people that
I've been fortunate
enough to work with,
the colleagues, and when I say
colleagues, I mean the students.
The students are my colleagues,
then it's been the best
it's been the best.
I've learned more from
them than they would
learn from me.
So it's about that.
It's about having
that elimination
of hierarchy, if anything,
my golden rule is
my job is to earn
the students respect by the
period of time that we have.
And if I've managed
to achieve that,
then that is the achievement.
But that is my job.
They by default, they already
have my respect by being there.
My job is to earn their respect.
And in eliminating that
hierarchy, it keeps me honest.
It keeps me trying my best.
It keeps me not cutting corners.
It keeps me giving it
everything I've got.
That doesn't mean that
every time I succeed.
But the one thing
that students will
hopefully take away from
any experience they
may have had with
someone like me is that
Jason tried his absolute best.
And that's for me, what
it all comes down to.
And part of that is creating
spaces where people can be
their authentic selves,
where they feel this
sense of belonging,
where they feel they are part
of a a culture, movement.
They're part of
something special.
And you can do that by
something as simple as
asking someone how their day has
been or embracing someone.
You know, I remember when I
first started teaching
higher education,
someone said to me,
like, dating night,
you shake a lot of hands
and give a lot of hugs.
I don't think you're
allow to do that.
I like it says who? So it's who,
like, like, it's important.
These things are
very, very important.
And that ability to
be one of the people,
you know, because I
always say to students,
like, this isn't everything.
This isn't everything.
Like, you know,
the most important
thing when you
come out of here, secondary to,
you know, this is, you know,
becomes this goes first
and before you know,
have a good degree that you
want to be global citizen.
You want to be a good ancestor.
You want to have
left an indelible
footprint on an organisation
or on a group of friends or on
a small influence of
people, you know,
and then you go into
the world and you take
that influence and you
make things better,
you improve things, you know,
and that's what it's all about,
or at least that's what it's
always been about for me anyway.
Yeah. Thank you, Jason.
There's so much in. It's
really, really inspiring.
And I think, you know,
that what I'm going
to take away from
that is absolutely that
every interaction matters,
whether that's whether
that's with a colleague,
a student, whoever it is
we come across, we can
make a difference.
And that, yeah, really,
really powerful,
really powerful stuff.
And For our students,
and I think as well,
that privilege,
actually, it is a real
privilege being an educator.
And it's almost the way
you describe it there,
a kind of vocation, isn't it?
You're kind of giving giving of
yourself to help our students
be the best that they can be.
Would you agree with that?
No, 100%. I mean,
I don't think I hope it's
a controversial belief,
but I think you're
born to do it.
I don't think you stumble
into this kind of thing.
Like, I Like, it's in your soul,
you know, to kind of
quote Rod Stewart.
It's kind of in your
heart and in your soul.
Like, it's there. It's there.
Like it's right.
It's right there.
And if you don't have it,
it's a very hard thing
to teach someone,
but it's there, you know,
and I think it's a difference
between somebody who makes
things in a pedagogical
space look effortless
and somebody that finds
it really difficult.
And that doesn't mean that
you can't learn to master.
You can master
anything, I believe.
But I think, you
know, when I see,
you know, the most
fluid practitioners,
the most fluid educators,
you can see that this is
what they were born to do.
But again, You know,
as my mom always said,
everybody's life has a purpose,
and everybody has something
that they're good at.
Everybody and everybody
has something
that they can become
good at, you know?
So there's always
promise in that.
And I really strongly
believe that.
But I do think it's a
vocation, and I do think,
you know, Like, it's
like a star in the sky.
I always believe,
like, you know,
like kids are a star in
the sky and they
choose their parents,
and sometimes you choose well,
sometimes you don't
choose so well.
But, I think it's like this.
I think, you know, educators
are like stars in the sky,
and you've got the kind
of education children
or education gods who are like,
right, you're going to
be here, and you're
going to be here, and
you're going to be here.
Like, I mean, these kind
of a theory of thoughts,
who knows if they're
true or not.
But like I do believe that.
I do believe it's in here.
You can't teach it.
You know, there's a reason why
there's two people can
teach the same subject,
and one group of learners
can learn from one and they
can't learn from the other.
There is actually
a reason for that.
And I think part of it is
because how people engage,
you know, and
that's a big thing.
And by the way, that goes
across any spectrum of life.
That's not exclusive
to education.
I think there's people who make
things look just
incredibly easy.
And the one thing
that I would always
say is that in academia,
Unfortunately, it's not an
easy thing for me to say this,
but it has to be said,
academia isn't a
particularly kind space.
And so when people see that,
rather than work
from the premise of,
I wonder what that
person has done to
master that particular art,
and, you know, pedagogy and
its literal translation
is the art of learning.
You know, what did somebody
do to master that?
And rather than kind of
engage from that premise,
people can often be
quite envious and can be
quite jealous and can
be quite resentful.
And I always tell
people, you know,
and I always often
say to students,
the most important thing is
to be secure in yourself.
If you're securing yourself, and
it's not an attribute
you all have.
And, you know, when talking with
colleagues and you talk
about collegiality,
you know, it's the emphasis
on sharing best practise,
you know, what works so well.
But to receive that
best practise,
you can't be operating
from a position of envy,
and you have to
be operating from
a position of
humility, you know,
and that if there's
one thing that
I would say academia
is bereft of,
is kindness and humility.
And, you know, if we
conduct a lot of what happens
pedagogically speaking,
I think setting those
really good examples is
important in terms of
what students take
away and the kind of citizens
they become when they go into
the labour market
or the real world
or even just into their
own lives, you know?
Absolutely, Jason.
Always be kind. I think.
There's no excuse
not to be kind,
and that's a challenge to
us all when you get busy.
In the modern
university environment,
but always, always be kind.
I absolutely absolutely
agree with you there.
Okay, let's move on
to the next question.
And I was just reflecting
there on, you know,
we've got colleagues in
the room who are
perhaps thinking,
you know, I'm not sure I can
live up to that lofty ideal.
I don't maybe feel
that it is a vocation.
I feel like I'm
just doing my job.
What are the sort of kind of
a few specific kind of maybe
tips and tips and tricks
based on your based
on your research,
based on your experiences,
tips to how colleagues
can kind of,
particularly in large classes,
you know, which is a
challenge facing us all,
how colleagues can can foster
that sense of inclusivity and
that sense of belonging
and mattering.
I think the word mattering
is really important
that every student feels
that they do matter.
I could you kind
of just, you know,
articulate maybe some concrete
things we can try and do?
Yeah, that's a difficult one.
I mean, That's really difficult.
Mm. Um stumped me that one.
I think Oh, I'm sorry.
No, no, no, no,
no, no, it's good.
No, it's good.
There's two things.
I think that people have lots
of different experiences.
Yeah. And so you
never want to kind
of speak in generous
terms to kind
of capture all of
those experiences.
But I think with
increasing classes and how
we make people matter,
I think one of the biggest
words and it goes both ways in
terms of for students and
for staff is tolerance.
I think because of
the business nature
of universities now,
staff and students have
become more intolerant,
but that is because of the
pressures that are placed.
And I kind of have
won a golden rule.
And my golden rule is that you
can't bag on people when
they're trying their best.
And I think sometimes I don't
think people appreciate
just how hard
staff try and just how
hard they are pushing
themselves beyond any
kind of capacity,
you know, and I
think I mentioned
earlier on about the
wheels falling off.
I also prefaced that by saying
a cautionary tale
of what not to do.
You know, it's not I think I
mentioned it several times,
it's not sustainable.
It's not sustainable.
And I wouldn't necessarily
I wouldn't advise
someone to do that.
I think that's part of it.
You've got a lot
of staff that are
pushing themselves
beyond their limits
because of these kind of
unsustainable
cultures where you've
got this influx of
students, you know,
in terms of you need the
influx of continuous influx of
students to keep
the machine going
financially and
economically speaking,
but it's putting more and
more strain on staff.
So I think collectively,
there needs to be an adaptation
of realistic expectations.
And I think part of that
is tolerance, you know,
tolerance and understanding what
people's limits are, you know,
engaging with people in terms
of finding out what that is,
providing pastoral provision
for staff who may be,
you know, at a point
of mental fatigue,
you know, physical fatigue.
I think those
resources need to be
invested in more because I think
more and more staff are
going off with stress.
More and more staff are
finding themselves in
precarious situations
in terms of employment,
and all of these
things have an impact.
And I always often think about
the colleague that goes
home So the day is finished
at like five or six.
What do they do past 6:00 P.M.
So when they get home, what's
the first thing they do?
And very often, I think what's
kind of quite normal
for a lot of people is
that they're still on their
emails till 10:11 P.M. And,
you know, that's the fear.
That actually the fear.
It's the fear of, you know,
I didn't quite do
this, so I'm getting
something wrong or I don't
want to get in trouble.
And I think that's a
really difficult position
for somebody to work from
to then try and pedagogically
inspire because you're
absolutely exhausted,
you're absolutely
drained and you're
bereft of any kind
of spirit towards,
you know, pedagogically
influencing or inspiring someone.
And I think there needs to be
probably more investment from
universities on
the pastoral side
of things to support staff
because I think what staff
are dealing with at the moment,
I'd go as far as to say
it's unprecedented,
and that's professional service
staff and academic staff.
So I think those things
are important because
invariably the people who
come most affected
are the students,
and the students are paying
significant sums of money.
And so you have that
kind of situation
where it's the tail that
waggles the dog that you know,
students expect the expectant
and I know people might defer
to that as entitlement,
but I think with generally
any type of business,
you know, you have the consumer,
and if they pay for something,
they expect something.
But I think there needs
to be an understanding
across the piece that's
just not as simple as that.
And actually, you know,
university staff are under,
you know, significant pressure
to negotiate the perils
of higher education now.
And obviously,
there's huge pressure
on students who are
paying, you know,
substantial sums of money,
particularly
international students to
reside in higher education.
And so because of that,
they want an outcome.
So it's kind of, you know,
the immovable the
irresistible force
against the immovable object,
and something's got to give.
And I think the
thing that can kind
of the thin wedge that can
bridge those two particular
immovable objects is
a greater tolerance by all
and how we impart that
is very difficult because
it's based on human beings.
It's based on how we
interact with one another,
the reasonable expectations
we have of one another,
and the tolerance
and the kindness
we exude to one another.
So it's not as simple
as kind of having
tangible things because apart
from anything else, no
situation is the same.
It looks completely
different from
one institution to the next,
and leadership is often
the thing that dictates
how those cultures
coexist or don't exist.
So there's all of those
kind of tenets and all
of those markers that
one would need to
be aware of anyway.
But I think tolerance would
be the most important thing.
Yeah, and I think, yeah,
absolutely. It is unprecedented.
We do we are
operating in really,
really challenging
times and times
that are in many respects
very different to how
things were when we began
our academic careers.
And I want to just kind
of think about, you know,
you're talking there
about tolerance
and some of the
strategies that we can
perhaps try and approach as
staff members to dealing
with the environment
in which we are.
But I would suggest to you
that all those things
around tolerance, kindness,
pastoral support are all things
that we can do
with our students,
we can afford to our students.
And maybe that's
where that's where we
need to head in terms
of thinking about mat
beloging and mattering.
So it cuts both ways.
It's for our staff.
I think for students.
I forgot to mention as well,
I think universities have
a duty of care to staff,
and I think that in all honesty,
universities have
completely abdicated
that duty of care to staff.
You know, there is there
isn't a line anymore.
It's almost like just
get the job done.
You know, there isn't
a boundary in place.
There isn't a, you know,
what universities
expect from staff
now is totally unrealistic.
And, you know, that duty of
care is hugely important.
You know, I don't
really think anybody
should be answering emails
in the middle of the night.
But that is what the
majority of people
I know in academia do, you know?
And I think universities,
you know, they have
a lot to answer for in
terms of that duty of care.
I think in the last five to
ten years in particular,
I think they've completely
abdicated that duty of
care to staff, you know.
Okay.
I want to I want to
think about innovation,
if that's okay.
One of the things that
we try and do through
this conference is
share innovations that
colleagues have done,
and we're trying to encourage
a culture of
education, innovation.
So I'd be interested
to know kind of
your thoughts on
how we innovate.
Aside from and I'm not I
absolutely agree with everything
that you've said up to now,
but given the constraints and
the challenges and the
difficulty in which we operate,
how can we attempt as educators
and with our students
to to think about
education innovation
in a way that helps
us foster belonging and
mattering in an inclusive way.
And how do we support
innovation that
especially helps kind of
minoritize groups of students?
What are your thoughts
on that, Jason?
That's a good question.
You know, I think,
um I was asked a few months ago,
what is the greatest sight
that you see on
a day to day basis or that
you've seen in your life?
And I remember thinking,
What a question.
I got asked this
doing a keynote and I
thought I stood there for
a couple of minutes and I
thought about it, and I thought,
I think the greatest
sight that I see,
or I have seen is
an unencumbered child
in the park playing.
They are free. They
are beyond free.
And when I think of
educative spaces,
that is our playground.
That is our pedagogical
playground.
And I think the
innovation comes from
being able to play, being
able to express yourself.
When you see that kid
in the playground,
they're expressing
themselves physically,
spiritually, they're
expressing themselves.
And I would like people to take
more chances in a
pedagogical space, you know,
expressions of that is
our playground as adults
that work as educators,
our playground is
the classroom space.
And I think a part of it is,
can you be childlike?
Can you be free in that moment?
You know, can you
shed, you know,
inhibition those
inhibitions that you have,
you know, as an adult, and
just be free in that space.
Can you be expressive?
You know, can you
perform? Can you sing?
Can you engage in dance?
You know, what kind of things
can you do in that space?
And I think in
terms of engaging,
particularly with ethnic
minority students,
I think, where are the
opportunities to bring in culture?
Into those classroom spaces.
And by the way, not just for
ethnic minority students,
everybody benefits from culture
and learning about other
people's cultures,
particularly ethnic
minorities because
I think within the British
context, very often,
those cultures can
be suppressed,
particularly in learning spaces,
as we already know.
So I think a huge part of it is,
you know, what do we
bring into that space?
You know, how do we use play?
How do we be that
metaphorical unencumbered
child in that space?
You know, and I think there's
lots of ways to do that.
I I I couldn't
prescribe a particular way of
doing it because I think
that sense of play,
that sense of being in
a childlike state is
very unique to an individual.
It differs from one
individual to another.
But for me, it's
about being emancipated,
it's about being free.
And every time, you know,
I'm in a classroom space or
I do anything that involves
some sort of teaching component,
I always think of it,
okay, like, you know,
I'm never going to
be a rock star,
but this is the closest thing
I might get to
being a rock star.
So I'm going to enjoy it. I'm
going to treat like a gig.
And so in my head,
that's what I do.
I play music before
students come in.
So it's like the warm up act,
you know, playing music.
And then I go on,
I'm the main event,
or I try to be, and then
realise my place is
to be a backing singer and
the students are the main event.
And you try and enjoy it.
You try and make it as conative
as possible, you know,
and I think the best learning
happens when you don't
realise you're learning.
And part of that is taking
very benign things
and making them
relatable and then
underpinning them with
the conceptual and
theoretical components
that require them to,
you know, have the
formative part
of completing an assessment
or an exam, et cetera.
But the best learning that
takes place is that kind of
tacit learning where
you're conversating,
you don't realise these
things are happening.
And there is an art to that,
but part of that is
that idea of play.
It's that idea of
expression, you know,
and and just being free,
you know, being able
to express yourself.
And again, it's a feeling.
It's something you
take from within.
And I think it also
comes from a position
of not taking yourself
too seriously.
And I think in academia,
to be quite frank, people take
themselves very seriously.
That's not something that I
ever really suffered from,
because I never had to change
how I was to be in academia,
because I guess part
of my thinking or
I was very fortunate to
have a background
as a PE teacher,
and a big part of what I did
was around fundamentals
of movement,
physical literacy, understanding
how the body works,
understanding how
learning takes place.
You take some of those principles
into a learning space,
and it just so
happens, you know,
go figure, people like
to feel like they can
express themselves.
You know, and that's what I
mean about getting to
know people as well.
You tap into their interests,
and you can bring
those interests
into the classroom space,
again, making someone feel seen,
making someone feel
like they belong.
So when I ask students
benign questions,
it probably seems quite
weird in the first instance,
but as the course goes
on and you bring
in their interest,
you can just see them
absolutely light up.
They light up. They love it.
And by the way, that's the
same with people who
aren't students.
The same with anyone
because again,
these principles just
apply in everyday life.
It's just like when we get
into classroom spaces,
pressure confines us to have
to be performative and to
engage in what I think is
a performative pedagogy.
But you don't have
to do that. I mean,
there's another
end of that, which
is just expression and play.
And just, you know, if you
enjoy it, they'll enjoy it.
And I've always believed
that, you know?
Yeah, that's a
really good way to
end that question the answer
to that question, isn't it?
If you enjoy it,
they'll enjoy it.
And yeah, I love that kind
of call for us to be more
playful and freer within
that teaching space,
whatever form it is.
Thank you. Thank you,
Jason. Love that answer.
And that actually you sort of
started to get onto
their co creation.
You know, you
talked about asking
students questions and then
bringing their answers
and their experiences and
their cultures into
your teaching,
which is a form of co
creation, isn't it?
But it's sort of happening
it's just kind of happening by
osmosis rather than by
particularly structured fashion.
So I'm interested to know a
little bit more about that.
You know, what do you do
you how do you do that co
creation with your
students in the classroom?
I mean, how I
personally do it is,
I mean, besides the
obvious things of students
being a huge part of
the curriculum design,
all of those things.
I always work on the
premise that people know.
So I never make the
presumption that
I know more than anyone,
and I never have.
And so I always think
the best scenario,
and I always say this to
any students that I teach
is that if somebody
was to walk past the room
or the lecture room
or the classroom,
they wouldn't know
who the teacher was.
And part of that is because
the student could be
stood up there taking a lecture.
Or leading on an area, and
part of that is
empowering people.
You know, if they show
enthusiasm in the knowledge
area or whatever,
you create a platform
where it's an
interchangeable space.
Anybody can be not literally
metaphorically speaking,
literally leading from
the front, you know,
and it also demonstrates to
their peers that Everybody
is capable of doing this.
You know, everybody is
capable of doing this,
and learning is transient.
You know, there isn't a
figurehead for learning.
What there is is
knowledge exchange,
and that the conduit
knowledge exchange
comes from all of us.
It's not incumbent on
one person to do that.
It's not a case of, as
we mentioned at the
very beginning,
I talk, you listen.
It's a case of we
talk, we all listen.
And you talk, you
talk, you talk,
they talk, we talk,
and everybody listens.
So my whole thing is that
I've always, you know,
put students at the
front, you know,
and then in that moment,
being a student myself is
something I still do now.
And I remember
someone asking me,
like, why do you do that?
And I said, Why do I do that?
Because I don't know
everything. I don't.
And it's good to learn.
And in that space,
again, it's about play.
And that goes back to having
the vulnerability and
the authenticity and
the humility to be in that
space and to to, you know,
make yourself small in
some respects and eliminate
the hierarchy, you know,
and you can do that in
a very physical way
because people perceive
hierarchy, you know,
there is perception,
and the perception
is the person stood at
the front is at the point
of that hierarchical arc.
And it's kind of like, no,
no, it's interchangeable.
We all are at that point
because no one everybody
is the same, you know,
and that for me is
quite important,
and it's something that
I've done my entire career
from when I started out as
a pe teacher to where I am now.
Gay, thank you, Jason.
I'm going to ask one final
question because I want
to allow a bit of time for
colleagues to ask questions,
and given the amount of
the chat is going
nuts, by the way.
So I'm sure I'm going to be
able to pick out questions.
So what I may do is
just ask people to put
their hands up and change
tack a little bit.
But one final question then.
You know, you've
spoken a lot from
your experience and what
you do in the classroom.
I'm just interested in if
there's anything you'd like
to add about, you know,
from your research on
anything else we can
do to contribute to
successful retention
and getting equitable outcomes
for all our students where
there's any final
thoughts you want to
offer up in those
important areas.
Yeah, that's a great question.
As a general of them piano,
and there might be
a couple of people
who might know me who
can attest to this.
I never talk about my research.
It's just not my way.
Okay. The only reason because,
um The greatest thing
about being a school teacher is
that you really exercise
this idea of practise.
So theory and practise.
And in academia,
you don't always actually you
can theorise about
a lot of things,
but the actual practise
of it is very different.
So if I was going to
talk about stuff,
I would talk about
it in relation to
practise in terms of
what that looks like.
And for me, one of
the things that
I I think is really
important in terms of
what we do in these kind
of spaces is going back to
our values and belief
system and what that
represents and what is
the reason why one
gets into something.
You know, what is the reason
why someone does something?
And I think that's always
got to be the compass point.
Particularly with the pressures
that are placed upon people,
I think that's really,
really important.
I also think it's about
having those intrinsic
drivers in terms
of what do I want my learners
to take from this space?
And again, that differs from
one individual to the next.
And it's very difficult
to kind of answer
those questions because
I think it genuinely
means different things to
different people and
how people kind of
perceive these things is
always uniquely different on,
you know, within
the geographical
context, within, you know,
the institutional context,
within the personal
context as well.
So I don't know
I don't think I've answered
that question very well,
but I think because it's a
difficult question to answer,
and it's not the kind of
thing that research alone
research wouldn't
necessarily provide
a buffer or an Elixa to
that particular question,
because the practical
bit is actually
the bit that is the
most difficult bit.
And that is more touch and feel.
That is something you gain
with experience, you know,
and you gain from maybe
observing or engaging with
other colleagues. Yeah.
And that touch and
feel element is very
much something that you it's
very, very difficult to explain.
It's in the air, you know?
Yeah. Yeah. And that
speaks to that, you know,
professional
artistry rather than
it's not a science, is it?
Yeah. There's art and
artistry at work.
And Thank you for that,
Jason. That was a good answer.
You've made me really
think about, you know,
research and practise when we
talk about evidence
based interventions.
But, yeah, we could continue
that conversation probably
for another half an hour,
but I'm going to
stop my questions,
and I'm going to open it up
for colleagues to ask questions.
And given that there is
so much gone in the chat,
could I just ask people
to pop their hand up,
and then I will get
through as many as I can
in the next 8 minutes?
Okay. So Katherine
Shepherd is first.
You're on mute.
Oh, Catherine, I still
can't hear you, my friend.
We still can't hear
you. You posted
your question in the
chat, Katherine.
I did see that. Don't worry.
I will ask it for you.
So, Jason, Catherine says
next week she's running
her first conference in
her school in the
law school here for
teachers of our feeder
colleges and schools.
As a former teacher,
what would you
prioritise right now in
these interactions between
school and college teachers
and university professors all
around easing transition
from school to college.
Anna thank you very much.
She's enjoyed your talk.
Oh, that's very kind
of you, Catherine.
And that sounds awesome, by
the way. That sounds brilliant.
And I think being relatable,
I think if you can demonstrate
that I've been in
your situation,
try and talk from that position,
try and almost be
a school aged or
a post 16 aged
student again and kind
of explain what that
transition was like.
And it's not necessarily
about centering yourself.
It's just about kind of removing
the distance between
you and them.
As in, I've been
where you've been.
I know it's difficult,
and arguably,
it's even more difficult now
than it was when I did it.
But these are some
of the benefits,
and these are some of
the things that can be
done in terms of this is
the potential pathway.
I think it's about relatability.
It's always about relatability,
and I think that
vulnerability and
authenticity will remove
a lot of perceptions,
and you never not you,
but I think none
of us ever realise
the impact that we can
have on someone with
just a few words in
terms of especially
when you're speaking to younger
people, and you're relatable.
And I think that's a
really important thing
because I think often when
people talk to younger people,
they talk from a position that
you've got to meet
them where they are.
And that's a very hard skill
to do because there has to
be a removal of ego and
a complete embrace
of vulnerability in
terms of humanising yourself to
a group of people
who fundamentally,
you have to meet
them where they are,
and there is, as Fiona said,
as well, there's an
artistry in doing that,
which I know for a fact,
you'll definitely
have Catherine.
Can you hear me now? Oh, okay,
I can hear you, Catherine, yes.
Correct. I think, yeah,
I'm meeting the teachers, Jason.
So I love working with schools,
and I know the government's
encouraging us to work
more with schools.
And I just feel like
it would take some
of the pressure off
our first year tutors,
and the schools are, you know,
we're knocking at
an open door as to
what we could start a
little bit earlier in
terms of independent
learning skills and
understanding what's going to
happen at university while
they're still at school.
So that's the plan. Yeah. And I
was just wondering as a teacher,
you know, whether there was
anything very specific,
you thought, I wish university
lecturers all knew this.
I know this as a
teacher, you know?
Such a good point.
Such a good question.
What do I, I
wish I wish university
lecturers knew
how to take how to
make things simple.
Yeah.
I think, you know, and I get it.
I understand it. That
is what academia is.
But I think because there's such
an emphasis on kind of sometimes
people postulating about
their own research
and, you know,
finding a way to funnel
that into, you know,
lectures and pedagogical
engagement through the guise of,
you know, and this is
the machine, right?
Like a research
informed teaching.
I don't I don't always
think that's the way.
I don't always think
that's the way.
And I'm saying that
as someone that,
you know, it's very rare,
if ever, if ever,
and I mean, if ever,
that I use my own research
as a proxy to try
and explain anything to
students because fundamentally,
what I want to do is to try
and take something that
is very difficult and make
it simple to understand.
And it's easier to do that by
making it relational in terms
of their own experiences.
So, for example, what has
your experience been
of discrimination?
And then I supplement that with
a conceptual framework
and a theory.
But it's easier if the
person can make it relatable
to their own experience because
someone might not have
had an experience,
for example, of sexism.
But if you get them to say,
if you get someone to, like,
have you had an experience of,
for example, ableism
before? Oh, yes, okay.
Right. And it's getting
people to kind of have
that empathy in terms
of that tolerance of understanding
someone else's plight.
And I think part of doing
that is you have to kind
of strip it back
and make it simple,
you know, and I think
sometimes Well, not sometimes.
I think in academia,
we make things
convoluted for making
it convoluted sake.
We do we do indeed.
Jason, that's fine.
Thank you, Katherine.
I hope that you
answered your question.
Got the time for
one more, Karen.
I know you put
something in the chat,
but do you want to
ask your question
very sort of succinctly,
and Jason can have a
short go at answering it.
Morning, Jason.
Thank you so much for
what you've done so far.
It's amazing to hear you
talk so passionately about
that humanization of
what we do as teachers,
as people that work
alongside our students.
And I want to
ask you specifically
about personal tutoring.
It's something that I am
really passionate about,
and it's understanding how
large our numbers are getting
within higher education.
What experiences has been
the best way of working
alongside our students?
Has it been from
professional services
or somebody specifically being
there as a personal tutor,
or would you say that
somebody on the course,
somebody being seen as
that person on the course,
they know they can go to
and they can rely on?
What are your
experiences of that to
try and make somebody feel
as if they really matter?
In 1 minute, Jason. Sorry.
I'll try and do
it in 30 seconds.
So, Karen, thank you so much.
I really appreciate
you, by the way.
And I think the best experience
I've seen of that is
a hybrid between
professional services
and personal tutors.
And I've seen that hybridity,
and I've seen that often
being the difference between
somebody staying at university
and completing their
degree and not.
And with the increasing numbers,
it does make it more
and more difficult,
unfortunately, because it's
almost like a GP appointment.
You've got a time
limit of 15 minutes.
But I think it's how
one uses the time,
and it's about how now
as a personal tutor,
you sign post students
to the right services and
professional services.
And they are also
overworked in terms
of professional and
pastoral services as well.
But I think it is
about kind of using that
as a trifector of means,
whereas before, I
think a lot of it
used to fall on the
personal tutor.
So I think it's kind of about
mobilising that even more,
but I understand how
strained those resources
are because there
are more students
and less of those resources.
Yeah, thank you. Thank you.
Brilliant. Right, Jason,
I've got 1 minute
just to say thank you so much
for coming to speak to us.
That was really,
really interesting.
And I've got so I've got
so many positive words
buzzing around my head now.
So I'd just like to kind of,
if we could just thank Jason
kind of with that yeah,
either hands or claps, I think.
Gentleman. That's
gone down really,
really well, and we're so
thankful for you
giving us your time.
I hope you've enjoyed this
fireside chat format.
I've really enjoyed doing it.
You've kept me on my
toes as an interviewer.
Fiona Bruce, I am not,
but I've done my best. You're
better. You're better.
Fiona Bruce, you're better.
But Thank you. I'll take that.
Brilliant. So yeah,
just thank you so much.
I'm sure Stuart will follow
up with you offline,
and I guess colleagues
can connect with
you if needed, with
their questions.
And I'm going to
encourage everyone now.
We're going now to a set
of parallel sessions.
So if you've got the programme,
you'll be able to choose from
a number of parallel sessions
and on with the conference.
What a great start. Thank
you very much, Jason.
Thank you so much, Trina.
You've been amazing.
And Valerie and Stuart
love you both load, man.
Thank you so much. Appreciate
you both. Thank you.
God bless everyone.
Have a great day.
To you. Thank you.
Bye. Right.
Right.